so we'll zero in hopefully we'll zero in
a bit on on this on this issue of
identity um so
yeah hi guys hello
so we might as well Rift to begin with
off some of the issues that Peter raised
um Jonathan maybe I'll start with you um
one of the things Peter pointed to is
the fact
that following decart and following the
enlightenment one of the presumptions we
made on the more humanist side was that
to be a human being was to be a mind and
maybe to be a linguistic mind a creative
linguistic mind and now we have machines
that
are credible and very rapidly improving
linguistic minds and so either they're
Human by that old definition or our
definition of human wasn't and teal
pointed interestingly back to
Christianity we didn't we weren't able
to develop that theme anymore but um I'm
curious about what you think we might
have missed in that too rapid
Association of the mind with the soul
and both of those with something like
linguistic competence yeah I think
that humans want things we have
aspirations we have goals and everything
that we care about is actually what
makes as human you know and that is why
the Ancients understood us as being made
in the image of God but in a relational
manner we look up and we desire to move
up towards something that transcends us
you know that vertical relationship was
the key to understanding identity and we
kind of we kind of threw that aside and
thought no we just need to be reasonable
beings and that's all that we need and
we took for granted the problem of how
identity is actually
aspirational right so so that identity
in in in that framing is part of the
Endless Journey up Jacob's Ladder let's
say and the identity you think identity
in a way since it defines what you are
or you could make that case sounds like
something static but the identity that
you're referring to is a continually TR
upward transforming identity towards
something ineffable the and you know
that because one of the issues we have
now is that we don't know where to place
our identity and that's the there's a
fight between identities identity is the
most explosive subject that you can talk
about whether it's talking about the
idea of what a nation is what a person
is what gender is what sexuality all of
these are related to Identity and if we
don't have this vertical there's a
competition where do I put my identity
is it my whims is it my nation is it my
sexual preference is it my family is it
you know where do we put it and that's
we've been seeing a fight of identities
for the past decades and we don't know
how to address it because there's so
many taboos around it as well let's
return to the issue of how we maybe
should do it and we'll let Mary comment
here about well your general thoughts on
identity and maybe some Reflections both
on what Jonathan said and what Peter had
brought up I think it's really important
to think a little bit historically about
what we mean when we talk about identity
um and it it turned out when I looked
into this a little bit for the paper I
wrote for this conference that identity
as in in the sense that we use it in the
Contemporary world is only really come
into common usage around the 1960s
really going back to the end of the
second world war and prior to that the
the concept that it replaced after the
second world war was the self um and the
concept that the self replaced in turn
as you go further down this rabbit hole
is the soul so we have a geneal iCal
relation between the soul is as the
ancient concept which which then
develops into the secularized self this
concept which came alongside actually
the cartesianism that Peter was
referring to where we begin to think of
the world as inert and dead and
ourselves as disembodied thinking the
the homunculus piloting the meats suit
in this inert and expressively dead
world and then in it's only really it's
with the digital Revolution which began
really in the 1960s with darpet um that
we began thinking of ourselves as
identities which is again something even
more fluid and malleable than this this
cartisian self and I think Peter's right
to point to the fact that we now need to
look Beyond this F this this very fluid
concept which has become so politicized
so commercialized and so individualized
to the point where it really doesn't
offer us anything to ground ourselves
with and and to look and really to look
outward again at grounding ourselves in
in the values and virtues that we need
to guide us okay so um and and really
and Peter referenced IM Margo and and I
think Jonathan you've you've spoken
before to how that really is the the
only the only concept left standing with
the robustness yeah to to to ground what
we're talking about and it sounds like
it's just sentimental or that it's
dealing with some existential issue that
we have but it's a structural question
right it is a it's a structural question
to understand how identity functions
Jordan this morning talked about how
identity is founded in sacrifice that is
there is this embedded giving up towards
the things that you care about and that
is the way that identity scaffolds into
each other and so you know if if go
ahead well that's associated I would say
with the abrahamic um the abrahamic
conception of Adventure so God the god
whose image were made in in principle
comes to Abraham as the spirit of
transformative Adventure right and he
makes four offerings to Abraham which
are very interesting they're very much
worth thinking about so God comes to
Abraham as the spirit of Adventure and
tells Abraham that if
he embarks on this transformative upward
striving sacrificial
Adventure then he'll be a blessing to
himself his name will become justly
renowned among his fellows so it solves
the status problem in the proper manner
he'll be handed both those benefits in a
manner that establishes something of
permanent and multi generational
enduring value that's what makes him the
father of Nations and he'll do that in a
manner that is not Zero Sum it'll bring
benefit to everyone else so you see a
conception of identity there that
imagine that the Jacob's Latter story
sort of establishes the notion of upward
striving towards the ineffable right
that's the destination of our
transformation and then those
Transformations are marked by sacrifice
and that the payoff for the granded
Venture is are those four offerings and
that's a that's an almost complete
definition of what you could say of what
it means to be human and certainly not
the cartisian pilot in a meat machine
let's say or the disembodied
intelligence and
so and and it and it it it's also not
something that seems to be exactly
grounded in this kind of cognition that
we can now abstractly represent it's
more like it's it's man and woman as
glorious Adventurer I suppose it's
something like that and actually if we
if we pick up on just to go on ragging
on cartesianism and the enlightenment
for a minute um what what the the
critical thing which allowed us to begin
this journey of technological
advancement which has brought us to this
extraordinary moment where we are now
was the abandonment of two of
Aristotle's four causes the so the so so
we we we kept the efficient cause and we
kept the material cause as ways of
thinking about what what what things are
and how things work you know what's made
of and what causes it what what what
what forces interact with what forces in
order to operate it but we lost but what
we lost was the formal cause what form
does it take and we also lost the final
cause what is it for um and those things
had to be discarded in order for science
as such to develop um and what that
means in practice once you Loop it back
onto humans is that we we have to
discard what what are humans for and we
have to discard what what a human is and
so so we abandoned meaning and purpose
and really this is what you you Al
knowah Harari mean when he says humans
we we we gave up meaning in exchange for
power it means we abandon formal and
final cause where humans are concerned
and I think if we're going to survive
the digital Revolution or you know
really to recover it and to recoup it to
to the benefit of humanity we're going
to have to do so having retrieved formal
and final cause for us for ourselves and
hopefully for the world as well but we
with
ourselves that's an interesting view of
the impoverishment of of identity I mean
if if the core of our Identity or or one
element of the core is aim and purpose
and you eliminate that from the playing
field let's say as a conceptual reality
then in so far as meaningful identity is
purpose and name you've taken that off
the table and that's certainly something
that's happening so we could delve into
that but there's another issue I'd like
to bring up too and I think this also
has to do with it's part
Protestant liberal individualism and
it's partly secularism is that and I
think my profession psychology has been
very guilty of this is that we've this
is even true for the more profound
psychoanalysts like Carl Yung we've
tended to think of identity as something
that's in your head like it's a state of
your mind it's something you carry
around internally and that's part of
that emphasis on the individual
but there are elements of identity that
are core that are clearly not in your
head in fact the the the most
fundamental elements of identity are
likely found in relationship yeah no
so you're married so that's your
identity you're a husband or a wife
you're a father or mother in
relationship to your children you're a
family in relationship to your local
community and you're a local community
in relationship to your city in
relationship to the state in relation
ship to the Natural order and then all
of that under God and I've increasingly
been viewing proper identity as the
harmony between all those embedded
relational systems and that's very
different than the identity that you
carry around in your head like you're
mentally healthy if your brain works
properly and there's something deeply
wrong about that because it's embodied
participation that's how we know what we
are we can experience it more easily
when we talk about how we're part of our
nation or part of our family it has it's
not just I'm a father I'm a father
because I embod I embody that role in
the world with my children and that's
what makes me a good father because it's
identity is also an aim and so that is
the difference that's why AI will always
be a supplement because it doesn't want
anything it only wants what we tell it
to want it has no body it has no death
it has nothing it has no drives and so
there even the reason the fact that
we're confusing
these AI models with true intelligence
and true agency means that we've
completely forgotten what it is to be
human that's interesting
because
well you see there's a there's a real
perversity about that or paradoxical and
almost comical perversity is that as
we've been able to mimic the most
abstract elements of human identity and
those as Peter said that we reflexively
identified with the human as opposed
let's say to the animal our ability to
use language we're finding our true
Humanity in the instinctual right in the
motivational drives and in the
embodiment that's underneath that so
it's like back it's back to the body
that's defining us as human as we
replicate our capacity to abstract in
machines and you know it it it I can't
help but think
that there's that's part of the deep
reason why in the Christian worldview
for example there's tremendous emphasis
on the sacrality of the body right
you're not a disembodied spirit and even
the resurrected the resurrected
individual is an embodied individual not
a spirit that's floating somehow
magically in some space that could be
duplicated in the let's say in the uh in
the digital world and that's because
identity has to be understood as the
Gathering of Multiplicity into Unity
that's what identity is and so it is
always embodied it has to be embodied
because that's what it is it's taking a
bunch of stuff a bunch of cells a bunch
of people a bunch of intentions and it's
joining them together towards a purpose
I think I'm more optimistic than you
about AI making us forget that we're
human I think what will actually happen
is that it will force the metaphysical
issue and we will we will learn the hard
way we'll we'll spend plenty of time
getting confused until we learn to draw
the distinction between computation and
comprehension but eventually it will
force the metaphysical issue in much the
same way as we we did our best to
technologized OS with the SE through the
sexual Revolution and we did our best to
technologized thumos through the the
Technologies of recognition in social
media you know all these different these
different ways of constructing a a self
to be recognized digitally on the
internet as this creature of pure
abstraction which has given us um sort
of the great awokening briefly and
hopefully now over maybe um um and and
we're going to have a we're going have a
go at technologizing logos that's what
that's what the a revolution and that's
what the doomers think the AI Revolution
is going to do that we're somehow going
to replace ourselves with a
superintelligence it's not going to
happen you know in the same way as the
the technologization of Aeros and thumos
just produces a sort of a strange
simulacrum but it doesn't actually
supplant the real thing and it doesn't
really nourish us it doesn't really um
you know it doesn't it doesn't really
improve on what we are uh Nei neither
will our technological simulacrum of
logos and eventually will force the
issue and it will and we'll we'll we'll
we'll work our way through the hard way
to figuring out the difference well
we're already stumbling over some of the
metaphysical difficulties that are
implicit in this technological
Revolution with the so-called problem of
alignment and so the problem of
alignment is well how do we determine
that these intelligent or these
cognition machines these large language
models have the same values that human
beings have or even that human beings
should or must have let's say in order
to survive and so now people are
grappling the tech the engineers are
grappling with really the domain of
values with the with the domain of
humanities and really theology they're
going to be stuck with that very r a
sense they're asking the wrong question
I think because you can't impart values
to a machine it's just so the idea is
ridiculous yeah well well let's take
that apart for a minute I mean there
there's it it's so it's it's such a
tricky thing to work out because on the
one hand part of the reason why you and
I can communicate and we can understand
each other and this this pertains to a
point that Jonathan made is that we
share a very deep biological platform
and so there's like if you say that you
were angry I don't have to ask you what
you mean by angry I ask you what you
were angry about and the reason I don't
have to ask you what you mean by Angry
is because I get angry too and so I know
machines have a simulation of that but
it's a funny simulation
because the pattern is there right like
they've got the the large language model
models have everything about anger
that's encoded in language and that's
encoded in relationship to all the other
encodings of of emotion in language and
so it it looks like the real thing and
it acts like the real thing but it
doesn't have this embodied reality that
is really well at least that's partly
what we're flesh out here that really
does make us human and that's it it
doesn't care doesn't have care no it
acts like it
cares but it's embodying our cares yeah
right and the problem I think that I see
is that we're precisely in this moment
when people are forgetting what it is to
be human they don't know where to place
their identity they've rejected the
image of God in us and now we're
increasing our power in these Tech
Technologies that feed back into our
identity making and so it's it's it's
this wild moment where in fact we would
need all the wisdom of the ancient
theologians right now but we've
discounted it we've said all this stuff
about non-human intelligence we don't
actually need to talk about it because
it's all Superstition and now we're
building a non-human intelligence and
yet if we're if we're willing and able
to bring formal and final cause back
into the picture in our eristic for how
and when we judge that it's appropriate
to use AI I think we we we can still
make it I really do I mean this is this
is an analogy which I I I offered both
of you earlier when we were discussing
this that there there is a critical
difference between giving your child an
AI language learning tool in order to
tune skills which he or she can then use
in practice with real people in the real
world that seems to me self-evidently a
a potentially very useful and beneficial
educational thing to do why not I I I
don't speak I don't speak Italian my my
child cannot speak Italian great um but
it that's a qualitatively fundamentally
different thing to say offering your
child an AI friend uh one of them is a
tool which enables greater relationality
with other people the other is a
substitute for other people which
collapses the distinction between the
machine machine and the person and to my
mind the Paramount task that we face now
is learning to tell the difference
between those two uses of the technology
that we now have at our fingertips yes
well God help us in that that difficult
Endeavor all right well we should draw
this to a close thank you very much for
that that's just a what we've just
barely scraped the service surface let's
say of identity in a digital world but
we made some Headway and well we'll
continue to do that in in our
conventions to come thank you very much
thank you for that yeah
y so